<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>True copies of the insolent, cruell, barbarous, and blasphemous letter lately written by the Great Turke, for denouncing of warre against the King of Poland: and of the magnanimous, and most christian answere made by the said king thereunto. With a short preface, declaring the vniust cause on which this Turkish tyrant, and faithlesse enemy of Christendome, now layeth hold to inuade it. Published in print by authoritie, the 11. of Iune. 1621</title>
            <title>Great Turkes defiance</title>
            <author>Ahmed I, Sultan of the Turks, 1590-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115263</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850482</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15690</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10526)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15690)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1163:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>True copies of the insolent, cruell, barbarous, and blasphemous letter lately written by the Great Turke, for denouncing of warre against the King of Poland: and of the magnanimous, and most christian answere made by the said king thereunto. With a short preface, declaring the vniust cause on which this Turkish tyrant, and faithlesse enemy of Christendome, now layeth hold to inuade it. Published in print by authoritie, the 11. of Iune. 1621</title>
                  <title>Great Turkes defiance</title>
                  <author>Ahmed I, Sultan of the Turks, 1590-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Purslowe] for William Lee: and are to be sold at his shop in fleetstreete, at the signe of the Golden Bucke, neere Sargeants Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The Great Turke" = Ahmed I.</note>
                  <note>Largely a verbatin reprint of: Sultan Ahmed I.  The great Turkes defiance.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes, with caption title: The King of Poland his ansvvere.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sigismund --  III, --  King of Poland and Sweden, 1566-1632.</term>
               <term>Poland --  Foreign relations --  Turkey.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15690:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15690:1"/>
            <p>TRVE COPIES OF THE INSOLENT, CRVELL, BARBAROVS, and blaſphemous Letter lately writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Great <hi>Turke,</hi> for denouncing of Warre againſt the King of POLAND: <hi>AND</hi> Of the Magnanimous, and moſt Chriſtian Anſwere made by the ſaid King thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a ſhort Preface, declaring the vniuſt Cauſe</hi> on which this Turkiſh Tyrant, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe enemy of Chriſtendome, now layeth hold to inuade it.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed in Print by Authoritie, the 11. of <hi>Iune.</hi> 1621.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Lee:</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Fleerſtreet, at the ſigne of the Golden Bucke, neere Sargeants Iune. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:15690:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15690:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout the Yeere, 1608. <hi>Ieremy,</hi> Prince of Molda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia dying, left 3. Sonnes, <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Alexander,</hi> and <hi>Bougdan,</hi> the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but 8. yeeres old, the Gouernment, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Minority, was by the deceaſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther committed to his Vncle <hi>Simeon,</hi> who dying within three or foure yeeres after, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the eldeſt ſonne, according to his right, and ſupported by the Councell of his mother, vndertooke the gouernment. At which time there liued at Conſtantinople, one <hi>Tomſho</hi> or <hi>Stephen,</hi> who falſly preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to bee ſonne vnto <hi>Aron,</hi> who had been Prince of Moldauia before <hi>Ieremy,</hi> had by money and other ſiniſter practices, framed
<pb facs="tcp:15690:3"/>to his ends, <hi>Mehemet Basſha,</hi> Lieutenant to the grand <hi>Viſier</hi> (which is the higheſt Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer vnder the <hi>Turk</hi>) and by falſly ſuggeſting that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> refuſed to pay the yeerely tribute of forty thouſand Chequines to the great <hi>Turke,</hi> obtained from him an Army of 20000. men vnder the conduct of a Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Generall, to expell Prince <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and eſtabliſh himſelfe in the gouernment. And notwithſtanding <hi>Conſtantine</hi> endeuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to giue all due ſatisfaction to this Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Generall, and made euident the fraud and falſhood of <hi>Tomſho,</hi> yet hee being alſo corrupted by <hi>Tomſho's</hi> bribes and great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, would admit no reaſon. Wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Prince <hi>Conſtantine</hi> making head to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelfe and Country, was in a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile ouercome, taken priſoner, and after, ſeeking to eſcape, drowned in the Riuer Nieſtre. <hi>Tomſho,</hi> after this victory, being thruſt into the Gouernnment, &amp; indeuoring to keepe by tyranny, what he had gotten by iniuſtice and vſurpation, the Nobility at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by armes to free themſelues and their Country from his vnſpeakable cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but with ſucceſſe vnworthy their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue;
<pb facs="tcp:15690:3"/>for, by an ouerthrow, both his malice, and the Countries miſery increaſed. In which diſaſter, the greateſt part of them fly into <hi>Poland,</hi> the refuge of the vnfortunate Princeſſe with her remaining children, and the Tribunall from which their country was in iuſtice to expect a Gouernour: the <hi>Polonians</hi> hauing by ancient Articles, and capitulations betweene the <hi>Turke</hi> and them, to the end their Kingdome might not be preiudiced by that neighbour Prouince, which though Chriſtian, was yet tributary to the <hi>Turk,</hi> reſerued to themſelues the right and intereſt to name a <hi>Vaiuod,</hi> or Prince ouer that Country. And to this purpoſe the King of <hi>Poland</hi> ſent an Embaſſadour to Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople, whom the Great <hi>Turke,</hi> contrary, to the Law of Nations, Turkiſhly anſwered by detaining him priſoner, and euer ſince hath threatened that moſt Noble, and Chriſtian Kingdome, with vtter ſubuerſion, hauing (as it is probably conceiued) to that end drawne all his forces out of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and made a greater leuy in <hi>Europe,</hi> then hath beene knowne in that Empire, conſiſting (by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port)
<pb facs="tcp:15690:4"/>of foure hundred thouſand men; an Armie ſufficient to ſatisfie the moſt coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, or religious Chriſtian Souldier with riches, or glory.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15690:4"/>
            <head>THE GREAT TVRKES LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>Sultan Achmat<lb/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST puiſsant, and higheſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of the Turkes, King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all Kings that dwell vpon the Earth, a King that dwelleth on the earthly Paradiſe, an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed Prince, and Sonne of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> Prior of the earthly Paradiſe, and keeper of the Graue of thy God, Lord of the Tree of Life, and of the Riuer <hi>Flisky,</hi> Conquerour of the <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donians,</hi> the ſeede of Great <hi>Alexander,</hi> Prince of the Kingdomes of <hi>Tartary, Meſopotamia, Media,</hi> and of the Martiall <hi>Georgians, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natolia, Bythinia, Aſia, Armenia, Seruia, Thracia, Morea, Valachia, Moldauia,</hi> and of all warlike <hi>Hungary,</hi> Soueraigne Lord and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15690:5"/>Commander of all <hi>Greece, Perſia,</hi> both the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia's,</hi> the moſt Noble Kingdome of <hi>Aegypt, Tremiſen,</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Empire, of <hi>Trabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zond,</hi> and the moſt glorious <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> Lord of all the white and blacke Sea, and of the holy Cities <hi>Mecha,</hi> and <hi>Medina,</hi> ſhining with diuine glory, Commander of all things that are to bee commanded, and the ſtrongeſt and mightieſt Champion of the wide world, a warriour appointed by Heauen in the edge of the ſword, a great perſecuter of his enemies, and of all their euill vices, a moſt perfect Iewell of the bleſſed Tree, the chiefeſt keeper of the <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified God,</hi> a Prince and Lord in whom the <hi>Mahometans</hi> truſt, and a great perſecuter of of all Chriſtians;</signed> 
               <salute>To <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>if thou doeſt deſire Our welfare, and art Friend to vs and Our Officer Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of all our forces which we will ſend, Our Greeting. But thou haſt long ſince broken Our friendſhip, and yet art neither ready nor fit to wage Warre, or fight battell againſt vs. But thou haſt ſome ſecret aduice and intelligence with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confederate petty Kings, and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, to deliuer thee out of Our hands, and our Vicegerents power, wherein thou haſt done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſedly,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15690:5"/>and indiſcreetly. If therfore thou thus perſeuere to oppoſe thy ſelfe againſt vs, then feare, for thy death, and the death of all thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is determined. <hi>Wee</hi> tell thee, <hi>Wee</hi> will ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thee, from the riſing of the Sun, to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe thereof, and we will ſhew Our Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty in our own perſon and ſight, vnto the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt parts of the earth; Our very thoughts ſhall be a terrour vnto thee, ſhewing that <hi>Wee</hi> will performe all that which <hi>Wee</hi> haue herein denounced. And <hi>Wee</hi> will make knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee the powerfulneſſe of our Dominions. And thou, O King, which putteſt thy truſt in ſtrong Forts &amp; Caſtles, ſhalt haue experience of Our reſiſtleſſe might. I will roote thee out altogether, and thou ſhalt behold this with thine owne eyes. Wherefore expect now no more friendſhip at my hands; put not thy hope in the ſtrength of thy walles, with thy owne forces and people. I will ruinate thee without any reſiſtance. I will deſtroy thy <hi>Cracouia,</hi> in ſigne of triumph, I will leaue there my bloudy ſword, that euery one ſhall take notice thereof, and my beliefe ſhall bee ſpread throughout all thy Dominions, and I will vtterly roote out the very remembrance of thy <hi>Crucified God.</hi> Let thy God bee angry, I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15690:6"/>care not; He may thou helpe thee. Thy anointed (the Prieſts) I will ſurely put to the plague; Wolues and wilde Beaſts ſhall ſucke the breſts of thy Women; thou ſhalt leaue and forſake thy Religion which thou now haſt; that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth of all things, ſhall bee conſumed with fire. Herewith reſt thou ſatisfied; I doe not tell thee now what I will doe; or meane to doe with thee; vnderſtand if thou wilt, or canſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Our moſt High Port of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> moſt ſtrongly guarded, &amp;c.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15690:6"/>
            <head>THE KING OF POLAND HIS ANSVVERE.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IGISMVND the third, by the grace of God King of <hi>Poland,</hi> Great Duke of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuania, Ruſsia, Pruſsia, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſouia, Samogitia, Liuonia, &amp;c.</hi> and Hereditarie King of the <hi>Suecians, Gothes,</hi> and <hi>Vandales,</hi> one of the moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruants of the True God, and of his Sonne IESVS CHRIST Crucified,</signed>
               <salute>to <hi>Achmat</hi> chiefe Prince of <hi>Turkes,</hi> &amp; Infidels, ſoules health.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>We</hi> haue receiued thy Letter, full fraught with threats, and ſwolne with impieties againſt the Maieſtie of the moſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15690:7"/>High God, whereunto wee had not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed anſwere, but that wee were perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, our ſilence would haue been a meanes of cauſing thee to flatter thy ſelfe ſo much the more, elſe had <hi>Wee</hi> neglected thee like an Arch-enemy of God, as thou art. <hi>Wee</hi> haue therefore thought fit in ſome ſort to regard the Saluation of thy ſoule, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thee to know, that thou art no other then a meere man, in thy perſon more weake then many of thy followers; which ſhould cauſe thee to remember, that if it had not pleaſed God to ingraue in the front of ſuch as rule, a kinde of awfull Maieſtie, whereby their ſubiects are kept in obedience; the good by reward, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and peruerſe by rigorous Lawes, and both the one and the other by Authoritie; it were impoſſible they ſhould continue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent aboue others. Thou then, who in thy ſelfe art but as other men, muſt know, that there is a Supreme Power of more might then thine, which doth vphold thy eſtate, cauſing thee to bee reſpected by thy followers. This power proceeds from God
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15690:7"/>moſt Good, moſt Iuſt, moſt Mighty, who preſrueth it ſo long as Princes humble themſelues before him; but if they ſuffer themſelues to bee tranſported with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and pride, he eaſily abateth, and corrects their fury. I will offer no other example to thy conſideration, then that of <hi>Baiazet</hi> the firſt, one of thy Predeceſſors, who thinking to ſcale Heauen with his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie (which in the iudgement of Man was vnreſiſtable, but in Gods ſight moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible) liued to ſee himſelfe vanquiſhed, taken, and impriſoned, coopt vp in an iron cage, (wherein hee vvas in triumph drawne after the victorious Conquerour, ſeruing him for no better then a footſtoole) and hauing no other food, then ſuch as was caſt him (like a Dogge) from his Table.</p>
            <p>Thinke then with thy ſelfe, that hee that vvas ſo great, ſo puiſſant, and ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, may haply by right of Succeſsion haue left vnto thee (as beeing deſcended from him) the like, or worſe fortune, if thou ſhalt dare to continue thy blaſphemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt GOD, and his Beloued Sonne <hi>Ieſus
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15690:8"/>Chriſt Crucified.</hi> Thou doeſt miſtake in thinking to lay an aſperſion vpon vs, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching vnto vs the Croſſe. For <hi>Wee</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it Our chiefeſt honour, and glory; by vertue vvhereof, as the Emperour <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> quelled his enemies, Wee hope, and aſſured our ſelues to bee defended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy Fury. Thy proud, and thunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring words diſmay vs not, our courage is more Maſculine and generous, then ſo to bee out-braued. For know, that wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard not thy threats, but vvith iuſt ſcorne tread vpon thy pride, and laugh at thy idle terrours, and in ſtead of thanking thee for aduertiſing vs before thy comming, We bid thee come when thou wilt, thou ſhalt bee receiued contrary to thy expectation. Wee haue ſteepe Mountaines, and impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Rockes that ſhall barre thee from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering into our Lands. Thou ſhalt finde our Cities, and Caſtles well furniſhed with Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, our Canons mouthes breathing fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fires, our courages inuincible, our blades eager and ſharpe, our bodies, as our mindes, prepared to ſuſtaine the violence of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15690:8"/>all ſeaſons, our hearts promiſing nothing but victory. And to dazell thine eyes, the glorious Standard of the bleſſed <hi>Croſſe</hi> ſhall goe before vs; but aboue all, the <hi>Crucified Son</hi> of the moſt High God ſhal cauſe his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to conduct vs, and giue vs the victory; He it is ſhall bee our Leader, vnder whoſe protection wee will not feare to braue thee at thy Gates. Thy miſcreant troupes ſhall be troden vnderfoote, and their bellies tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled on, and by a happy victory (if thou chance to eſcape our conquering Arme) thou ſhalt finde thy ſelfe purſued vnto the moſt ſecret Dens of thy abominable <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio;</hi> thou ſhalt ſee thy <hi>Moſques</hi> laid leuell with the ground, thy <hi>Muphty,</hi> and other the execrable Prieſts of thy perfidious <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> made Gally-ſlaues; all thoſe traiterous run-a-gates whom thou doeſt harbor, ſhalt thou ſee put to exquiſite torments; of all which be moſt aſſured. And then ſhall bee ſet free all thoſe poore and miſerable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who now lie groning vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of thy Tyrannous yoake, whoſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cryes being mounted to Heauen, haue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15690:9"/>iuſtly excited the vengeance of God vpon thee, who hath permitted thee to riſe to this height of pride, that thy ruine &amp; deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may bee the more exemplar vnto after-ages. To conclude, thou ſhalt ſee the ſeruice of <hi>God</hi> re-eſtabliſhed in <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> which thou doeſt now vniuſtly vſurpe. But if it happen thee to end thy miſerable life in Battell, (which we hope <hi>God</hi> will grant) be confident, that all the foreſaid vengeance ſhall enſue vpon thy death; And whiles thy wretched Soule lies broiling in the quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe flames of Hell, wee will lift vp our cheerefull voices, and, for the victory ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ouer thee and thine, ſing praiſes vnto our <hi>God:</hi> to whom be all glory for euer.</p>
            <p>Know then, O Infidell, that we feare thee not at all, and if thou beeſt not wilfully bent to runne headlong vnto thy owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, be aduiſed; content, and containe thy ſelfe within thoſe bounds thou doeſt at this preſent vſurpe, and if thou haſt any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe at al that thy thrice reuerenced Prophet <hi>Mahomet</hi> could tell a truth, or foretell fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture euents, then call to minde, that of thoſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15690:9"/>thouſand yeeres which hee preſcribed for the continuing of thy Sect, there remaine not aboue ſixe or ſeuen yeeres. This then is the time that the yet vnſheathed Sword of the Chriſtians affords for thy amendment, that thou mighteſt come to the knowledge of the alone True GOD, to worſhip him in his Sonne IESVS CHRIST, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto we once more exhort thee, omitting all other ſalutation, and commendation.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at our Caſtle of <hi>Poſnwich,</hi> &amp;c.</dateline> 
               <signed>SIGISMVND.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Publiſhed <hi>Iune</hi> 11. 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
